<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: pragprowrimo | Seeking Simplicity]]></title>
  <link href="http://mattstine.com/blog/categories/pragprowrimo/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mattstine.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-28T23:21:40-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://mattstine.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Matt Stine]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hi, I'm Matt Stine, and I have technology ADD...]]></title>
    <link href="http://mattstine.com/2009/11/03/hi-im-matt-stine-and-i-have-technology-add/"/>
    <updated>2009-11-03T16:50:16-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://mattstine.com/2009/11/03/hi-im-matt-stine-and-i-have-technology-add</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yes, it's true. I came to the realization that there is such a thing as TADD...technology attention deficit disorder. Ironically, I came to this realization while reading a sample chapter from the upcoming book from the Prags, <em>Pomodoro Technique Illustrated: Can You Focus - Really Focus - for 25 Minutes?</em> You see, it's Pragmatic Programmer Writing Month (<a href="http://praglife.typepad.com/pragmatic_life/2009/10/prag-pro-wri-mo.html">follow the trail that begins here</a>), and I finally set aside an hour today to begin writing. At present, I just can't make up my mind what book topic I want to focus on. I have the following in mind:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Polyglot Programming</p></li>
<li><p>Agile Testing Strategies</p></li>
<li><p>Groovy/Grails Automated Testing</p></li>
<li><p>Functional Programming in a JVM World</p></li>
<li><p>Or, perhaps, a topic that hasn't churned up from my R-mode brain yet...</p></li>
</ul>


<p>So, I have decided that I want to write an article detailing my development of <a href="http://www.duckduckgoosedesigns.com">http://www.duckduckgoosedesigns.com</a> in Grails, an article that I hope will appear in an upcoming issue of Groovymag. It seemed like a good idea - write on something that I know very well and that I think could be helpful to others. Not only that, but it just might prime the writing pump for a bigger work like, maybe, a book! So, as I started writing, it occurred to me that I needed to let WebDevPub know that the entire source code for the online store was available at GitHub, so I jumped into the article submission site and added a note. This reminded me that I had not yet applied license headers to my source files, so I jumped into IDEA to use the Copyright Plugin to do so. It was at this point that I figured out that the Copyright Plugin does not support Groovy or GSP files, so I decided it would be a good idea to write a Grails script that would automatically do this. In the process, I decided to jump over to TweetDeck and let the world know of my intentions. It was at this point that I realized I had not yet followed @praglife on Twitter, so I fired that off. Realizing I wasn't quite sure of the @praglife Twitter handle, I jumped over to the blog, and while looking for it noticed the news item about the Pomodoro book. I clicked on it and downloaded the sample chapter on interruptions. While scanning through and reading about internal interruptions, I realized that I was in the middle of one. My simple task - to focus on writing an article, had been interrupted by a stream of internal interruptions that led me to reading about internal interruptions. I have TADD. I'm out of denial, so what's the next step? ;-)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
